[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-
radio.net se radio is brought to you by
the it computer society and by It
software Magazine online at computer.org
[Music]
software welcome to software engineering
radio I'm your host bries amanat today's
session is about streaming databases
understanding what it is benefits of
using it and the challenges unique to it
our guest today is ying Jin Vu who is a
founder of rising wave Labs building the
product Rising wave which is a
distributed SQL database for stream
processing prior to Rising wave Labs
yingjun was the software engineer at the
red shift team Amazon web services and a
researcher at database group IBM El
Madden Research Center y Jun welcome to
the show hi hello everyone thanks for
having me here I'm in yes I'm a founder
of Regin W labs and I'm a database guy
and a stream processing guy so really
excited to join show let's start with
the fundamentals can you provide a high
level overview of what are streaming
databases well streaming is a base well
definitely is more about stream
processing but it's not just about a
stream processing engine it is a
database system so people may heard
probably have already used some stream
processing systems like P fling prob
with back streaming right but for
writing wave it basically exp provide
the people with the experience of a
database experience for processing
streaming data in the other way it
actually allows people to process
streaming data inside of database so
this is fundamentally different from the
stream processing engines because
streaming database actually stores data
which means that we can essentially
process to the input and output of the
stream processing jobs and then do data
serving inside of databas system so and
so for writing with specifically as a
streaming database it is post compatible
which means that okay as long as you
have system that can talk to postgress
this system is high likely to be able to
talk to Rising wave so which means that
K or Rising W can connect to a lot of
systems in the postgress ecosystem right
and what is the problem that we trying
to solve by using streaming databases
well the streaming databas definitely
tries to solve the stream processing
problem so what's a problem of stream
processing well there have already a lot
of stream processing systems right for
par flank and the spark streaming but I
think the key problem here in today's
world is that this type of systems are
kind of first difficult to use and
second they are not very cost efficient
so let's talk about the EAS of use first
when we try to use a big data system
like spark or Flink well we need to
think about okay how to how to write
Java right and people may argue that
okay these systems have already provided
a python API probably SQL API and then
probably can directly write C code or
python code but fundamentally you
actually need to match a jvm based a
system and more importantly the thing
here is that okay you actually need to
understand the fundamental concepts
inside of this stream pres systems like
you need to understand okay what is
checkpointing what is well how we can do
phot and how we can do scaling right you
need to know how the system work
internally but in writing wave people do
not need to think a lot of things about
this right think about well if you're
using postgress you will never need to
worry about okay how the postgress
process the transactions right and if
you use postgress you will never need to
worry about okay what is checkpoint and
what is fail recovery right you just use
it and you just write SQL code that's
fundamentally different from using let's
say system FR Spar I'll probably
probably flame right that's fundament
and second thing here that will cost
efficiency so when we talk about for the
spark of Flink right in this kind of Big
Data Systems where we people are talk
about okay map reduce right we try to
shuffle the data data and Shuffle the
data into mple machines and ask every
single machine to their local
computation and then we do at agregation
right such kind of Architecture is
highly optimized for performance which
means that K ke I can give you 10
machines and this kind of system will
achieve the best performance by running
on top of these T machines but what we
saw in today's world is that people use
cloud so we never need to worry about
okay how many computer nodes we can get
right as long as we pay money we can get
as many computer node as we want right
but the thing here is more about the
cost efficiency how that is how I can
reduce a cost why that's important
because well I mean people don't really
want to spend let's say always spend a
lot of money on a data system and they
just want to provision a small amount of
machine that just fits to their workload
right if let's say that I have a small
work I don't really want to spend 10
machines I just want to provision one
single machine for the system and in the
Stream processing World The key thing
here that streaming workload can
fluctuate think about where if you're
using Uber right for think about where
you be using some let say linking or
some other Twitter right the workload
can fluctuate right A lot of people will
Vis the website in the morning but very
few people were Vis the website at
midnight right that's a that's a that's
a traffic and that's a that's how why
the workload can fluctuate in the Stream
processing world we really want to
achieve let's say so called Dynamic
scaling which means that we really want
to just a provision as much Resource as
needed right we do not need to provision
a lot of computer nodes and we just want
to provision computer node that can fit
into my that can support my workload so
yeah to summarize resing waves tries to
address the EAS of use problem as where
as the cost efficiency problem right and
what's the tradeoff for achieving the
cost efficiency well well definitely
there are some tradeoffs from the
vendors perspective right because we
weild the riding wave ring wave is open
source database and from the ERS
perspective we actually need to spend a
lot of efforts in building both the
comination layer and the storage layer
it takes a long time we actually have
already spent three years in building a
system and now it works and it has been
deploying hundreds of clusters in
production but we all know that it's not
building one day I mean we have to spend
a long time to build it and second thing
here that okay in terms of the trade of
we actually need because we store data
we use the architecture called so called
the cop computer and storage
architecture and in this architecture we
actually need to store the data in
remote object stall let's say S3 and S3
is kind of slow right so if we want to
support latency sensitive applications
like stream processing applications then
we actually need to think about okay how
we can avoid accessing S3 right so which
means that we actually need to build
pretty SP caching mechanism but if you
use soall the computer and storage cupo
architecture you don't need to worry
about that because everything is insted
in local machine right so that's a
tradeoff so for Big Data System like map
reduce basa system like Hado Sparks
Flink they are actually optimized for
for performance well for performance
probably a secondary but we always take
care of the cost efficiency we always
need to think about okay how we can
achieve the best in terms of the cost
efficiency that's a tradeoff so if I
understood that correctly Rising wave as
a streaming database which uses the
cloud as the data store in this case S3
and that allows you to scale in you know
as per demand and that's basically where
the cost efficiency comes in and the
tradeoff is obviously in being able to
being able to store data in S3 and that
would be the latency or the speed of
operations yes yes well I mean if you
want to store data in S3 then definitely
accessing data in S3 is kind of slow
right but here I would like to mention
that I just I mean use S3 as an example
right because people can store data in
gcp or probably can store data in a
right if the pr they actually can store
data in hdfs right or probably some
other object store right we actually
support all those object stores but all
these object and stores have the Traer
right well they they can start a lot of
data without spending a lot of money but
they're kind of slow so ring wave is
built on top of this object Stars so we
actually need to figure out how we can
achieve the high performance when using
such kind of store as a storage right
taking a step back obviously Rising wave
is close to your heart because you have
founded the product you are the founder
of the company but what are the various
streaming databases available in the
market Okay so we talk about this thing
where people will say Okay streaming
processing or streaming database is a
new thing right so it's actually not to
be honest stream processing the concept
of stream processing Harry was first
invented in University in emia and
people in emia was thinking about okay
how we can support monitoring
applications using database systems and
that's why they think about okay whether
we can instead of just processing bat
data whether we can process streaming
data inside of the database and then
that's why they build a such kind of
thing called a streaming SQL and a lot
of database to manage streaming data and
that happened in 2002 so streaming
database have already been involved for
20 years but at the very beginning it
was for all these for Academia projects
like I can name a few like stream like
Aurora like bores they are all streaming
devices built in Academia and then IBM
db2 and Oracle as well as microsof secet
server all incorporate the concept of
stream processing into their database
systems so I think where they actually
have the product for like Microsoft
streaming Insight it is essentially a
streaming database but people talk a lot
about a stream processing engine like SP
streaming like samsa like Flink I think
for all this system were inspired by map
ru right which uh was a paper published
by Google in 2004 and what they try to
address is that okay whether I can
process streaming data in big scale
right I probably really want to process
the streaming data in let's say we using
a Sol machines right 100 machines are
SOL machines right and they do not
really want to manage storage so they
build such things but see because of the
cloud and because of the yeah all kind
of the reasons right people come back
and say that K luck where I probably
really want to have a system that
provides a simpler UI or simpler
interface and all I can use a database
system to process streaming data so
people just come back and build a system
called the I think well one of the
famous systems is called a pipeline DB
and pipeline DB it essentially provides
a plugin for postgress and which allows
users to directly process streaming data
inside of the p and that's Pon DB and
another notable system I would like to
mention is KQ DB kqb is actually a
database built on top of cka that is
well if you are a Kafka user you can
actually directly use casq DB to process
your Kafka data using CCO and that's
another pretty famous streaming datway
systems and there are some others like
materialized and uh recently I heard of
some other stre base was eded but
definitely raing wave is among them yeah
it's one of the probably best in my
opinion is definitely one of the best
streaming is nowadays yeah absolutely
considering it's quite old right I
didn't realize that streaming databases
were that old but do you remember any
use cases or you know any stories where
your users or clients have migrated from
a traditional database to a streaming
database so if we talk about for the
users then we actually are two type of
users one type is from the Big Data
world and the other type is from the
database world so from the Big Data
world I mean that people probably use
Flink or probably use Spar streaming and
then they move to ring wave and uh you
know database world I mean that people
probably use post and then or probably
have some other database systems then
move to resing wave so you talk about
the second type right moving from the
existing database to streaming database
so we did did see that so I can give you
a few examples one of our customers
actually use post gr initially and they
actually heavily use postgress M views
to support dashboard but the problem
here is that a postgress m view is not
incremental that's the first thing and
second thing here that you actually need
to continous see tricker refresh to
refresh and motorz VI in post grass I
know that's where there is Improvement
in the post grass community but for I
mean in many Cloud product they do not
really support for the let's say the
incremental Miz views are probably
something like like Auto refresh so they
think that okay I mean it's kind of
difficult to use so they move to ring
wave because ring wave provides a really
nice M view that Cas is consistent and
always display the reonal data Al the
display the fresh result and that's one
of the reasons why they move from post
to resing wave and second reason here
that they actually don't really want to
maintain M use or secondary indexes in
their oper dat bases such as let say my
or post or mongod DB the reason here
that okay if people use my SQL post they
are actually supporting their online
traffic right where they are supporting
their online applications and this kind
of applications consume a lot of
resources right if you build a materal
view inside of the operational database
then what it means that the materal view
where actually also can consume a lot of
resources and it will actually compete
the resource the online traffic so
people don't really want to see that so
that's why they need to have a dedicated
system to do that and actually we also
saw some other reasons people move from
the optional database to the streaming
database for example okay one of our
customers say that okay they think that
their post gr is too slow in terms of
when ingesting streaming data right
think about well if you have a cka and
then you consume data from kavka and
then injest it into postgress then
postgress may not have the capability to
consume so much data within just a
pretty short period of time right but
for writing wave riding wave is actually
designed for consuming streaming data
from let's say systems like Kafka like
some kineses right so we actually can
support real time ingestion and that's
definitely a big win compared to
existing datas systems like post my so
right couple of questions bases that for
the benefit of our listeners can you
explain what a materialized view is well
materialized view is definitely a pretty
fundamental Concept in a database system
when people send a cury people can write
SQL right like select star from table
right but the problem here that if you
do this kind of thing then every time a
human need to trigger such kind of Curry
right but sometimes we really want to I
mean we really want to ask our database
to autoly to refresh result for me right
I probably really want to see the
probably a result of a curing right then
what I can do I can just create a Miz
view inside of database system so that
get and then after you create a Miz view
then the system can automatically
consume data from probably your tables
or probably your Upstream services or
probably some other Data Systems and
then do the computation and then persist
the data
inside of materal view you can also
think of materas view as let's say so
called a special table a special data
table inside of a database system which
can do the computation and show you the
result and that is materal view got you
also mentioned that in some cases post
is too slow in ingesting data can you
help quantify that what is too slow you
know how do we quantify that okay so in
the Stream processing world there's a
concept called lock or probably back
pressure so what do it mean that okay
let's say that if we maintain a cka and
then we want to use a post to consume
data from Kafka then let's say that we
have already generated the Kafka service
service have already generated a t but
for post grass it only consumes let's
say 100 twoos right at same time so
which means that okay there are 200 two
P that remains in TKA that is not
consumed by postgress so as a Time FL we
can think of like okay actually there
are more and more data will be produced
by Kafka right so if postgress cannot
catch up with Kafka then it means that
there is a huge backlog inside of kfka
and we will never catch up with the
latest data and we will never see the
latest result in the postgress so there
will be a lagging inside of Kafka inside
of postgress okay we'll move on to the
next section where I want to focus on
some of the architectural principles or
thinking behind streaming databases
we'll start with you know what are the
fundamental architectural differences
between a streaming database and a
traditional database if you ask me about
the difference between a streaming
database and a database system then I
say that for streaming database it
always do compination first and then
store data but for a database system it
always store data first and then do a
competition so I can give you example
let's say in the stre datase like KB or
like ring wave we actually ask people to
create M views first and then once you
create M view once new comes in it will
be consumed by the ring wave we do
directly do computation and refresh
materal View and then the data will be
persisted in raing wave option
definitely I mean which means thate the
user can determine whether they want to
stall data or not but in a conventional
waye well it's actually automize for use
case where the data is first stored in
the table right so if I insert a tupo
into a table then the tle will be
persisted after I have already inserted
a bunch of tupos then I can send a hog
CS like select star from T right to
carry the table inside of a database
system so that is that's the fundamental
difference between the streaming
database and the database system right
got it and how does a streaming database
handle changes in the data structure or
the underlying schema okay so now you
talk about the schema change right well
in I think it definitely varies
depending on which system you're talking
about but if you ask me about Ring wave
then I have to say that okay ring wave
does a schema change in the same way as
a postgress which means that okay I mean
if you want to do I mean schema change
drop a column or probably add a new
column to a table then it will just uh I
mean handle the data change or the
schema change in the same way as post
does there's no difference at all right
and you specifically call out that's the
case for Rising wave so are there other
ways for dealing with schema changes in
the streaming World actually in the
streaming world when we talk about the
data change then sometimes we refer to
the data change or the schema change in
the Upstream Services right the reason
here that for streaming database well
one of the main data sources are
actually databases operational databases
as I just mentioned earlier right so
let's say that you have a post in myod
and now you have a downstream streaming
database like Rising wave to consume the
data from your postgress or my CLE then
in this case people can change the
schema in my SQL and postgress right so
R will will actually detect the schema
change and adapt to it let's say that if
you add a new column in your post system
and resing wave will inity processor
data and then it would actually detect
that okay there's a data change there's
a schem of change in my Upstream service
and then I will add a column accordly
based on my Upstream services but again
we have to say that well that's how
reading wave handles the schema change
of the Upstream services but definitely
there are some other systems streaming
databases and which actually do not
really support schema change but if they
want to support schema change then I
think where they likely support in
schema change in the same way as writing
with does right how is low latency
achieved in a streaming database well
low latency is achieved by using
incremental computation there also a
fundamental part between the streaming
database and the conventional database
system in a conventional database system
if you issue a cur like select star from
T or okay or select con star from T
right you actually do full compitation
which means you will actually need to
scan the entire table and then do the
computation and show the result to users
right but for reading wave and other
streaming databases if you define a
materal view like create materal view as
select const from P then this kind of
streaming devices will always do
increment commutation which means that
every time a new Tu comes in and is
consumed by the stre database it will
modify the result by just applying a
data to the existing result it will not
do the competition from scratch it will
not do that so if we do incremental
Commendation then it means that okay we
only need to care about the new data
right we do not need to care a lot about
historic data right because for the data
the result has already been there right
so if we only need to deal with let's
say a small amount of data small amount
of newly inserted data definitely we can
do the competition in very low latency
right and the way you know that its new
data is by storing State and because
it's a database you're able to do that I
know that case okay so there are
definitely multiple ways to detect
whether it's a new data based on the
database for example I used to work in R
shift and the r that detects a new data
by scanning a table and identify okay
where the new data is and but for Rising
wave it detects a new data differently
because raising wave will directly
consume data from Upstream Services it
will the newly inserted data will
actually be buffered by resing wave so
that case I mean resing we will
essentially know which new data has
already been inserted or probably which
new data change let's say delete or
update will need to be handled by resin
wave so actually it detects that this is
kind of a new data or new notifications
using buffers in Rising wave and while
we are talking about latency is there a
sliding scale of latency which drives
the choice of database or rather the
processing choice so you know at one end
of the spectum you would have a
requirement that you know you need the
data to be refreshed or to be updated
only you know at the end of the day and
that's where you have the patch
processing what does that scale look
like and where does streaming databases
fit in that sliding scale yeah if feel
okay so that's a definitely a great
question so in many use cases people
probably do not really care about the
latency right well people people do not
really care about the freshness let's
say that if I want to do financial
reporting right people do Financial
reporting monthly right or probably even
quartly they do not need to see fresh
results right if I made some changes so
I'll probably I purchase some new
product I probably do not need to report
do not show this purchase in my report
instantly right so I can just show this
kind of change for in my monthly report
or C report and in this case people do
not really care about the latency right
what people do not really care about the
freshness and in machine learning I mean
some people also do not really care
about the fresh is right I can probably
use Lots your data to chain a data model
right for sure I can do that but
definitely there are a lot of use cases
where the freshness is required so I can
give you a couple of examples one is the
let's say Uber right well I mean Uber is
definitely a great example right for if
I want to call a taxi mover then I
definitely really want to have someone
to take my order right instantly right I
don't really want to say that okay I
want to grab a w but well it takes me an
hour to grab a taxi right so it's
definitely not a very good user
experience and there are some many other
use cases like stock dashboarding right
so if I want to show my stock St uh show
the changes in the stock market I don't
really want to just show people the I
mean the last days results right I
definitely want to show the I mean the
result of the the stock market within
the last 1 minute or probably even 1
second right so I don't really want to
see any lagging there right and
definitely there are some other pretty
interesting use cases like manufacturing
we actually have a pretty big
manufacturing customer who produces the
modro a device electronic device they
actually have a lot of factories across
the world and what happened previously
was that before introducing stream
processing into a company was that okay
they actually need to make phone calls I
mean that was probably 10 years ago and
they actually need to make phone cars to
directly talk to people in a factory and
okay check okay what happened they make
such kind the phone call every 4 hours
or 6 hours to check the status but they
found that okay no it doesn't really
work the reason here that okay I mean I
really want to see the latest status
right let's say that okay if there's
some anomaly occurred in one Factory
then I probably really want to pass the
entire pipeline right or pass the in
production pipeline right because I want
to check okay whether there's some
anomaly or some misfunction right or M
function right so yeah and then use the
stream processing system first actually
PP on DV and then they move to some
other systems there and then recently
move to writing W and once they adopt on
the streaming databases for what Chang
it to them is that okay they actually
can just sit in the office and then see
the dashboard and to see okay whether
there some novity occurred within the
last few seconds so that's how stream
processing changes world and how
streaming
dally support help them to better manage
their product line so if I try to
quantify the that what we're saying is
if the requirement is to be able to
process data from seconds to minutes you
would look at streaming
databases and if it's more than that an
hourly or a daily job that would be most
probably patch what about use cases
where you want to process your data in
Nan seconds or milliseconds is that
something which would still be a
streaming database use case for NCS and
and probably microsc we actually see
some company do that with that is
trading firm trading firms really want
to process for I mean do transactions
right withing let's say NCS or micros
seconds but I don't really think that's
a pretty good use case for streaming
database because for for streaming the
base it's probably good for hand
supporting applications that record the
same milliseconds it will work but for
another seconds well I think I would
suggest to directly I mean build your
own system that's how all these trading
firms do actually all these trading
firms have their own specialized trading
platform to process the trading data
right with other the stock data in
microsc but we do see that the many
trading firms actually also D riding
wave we have several clients in the
trading world and they actually what
they do is that they actually use ring
wave to monitor the stock market for
them because they really want to see
okay whether there's some signal changes
over the last probably few seconds or
probably less than 1 minute right they
also want to check okay how many
transactions they have already done
within the last seconds or within the
last few seconds or within a last of one
minutes right they do not need to build
a specialized system for S kind of
applications and then but they do not
really want to use a batch system so
they choose to use let's say the
streaming database okay yeah so for high
frequency trading applications you have
seen forms use their own custom
application whereas for tracking the
stocks and other use cases like uber
stock prices manufacturing that's why
streaming databas is usually excel in
yes that's right moving on to the next
section which is around data inje and
processing what are the common protocols
or methods used in data ingestion for
data ingestion we typically ingest the
data from Kafka and all the messaging
cues or CDC the database CDC so for
Kafka well it's kind of like natural
because for I mean the C always St
streaming data so but for writing wave
and or for some other streaming
databases well they can directly consume
the streaming database from K from
message que and the other type is the
CDC the database CDC or the change loog
of the database system so for CDC I mean
people use CD because well they think
that they really want to directly
consume data from their databases let's
say that okay if we have a let's post on
my c i really want to capture the data
change and then consume these data
changes into ring wave right so ring
wave can do that and we do that to
called deum which is a two specifically
designed for CDC database CDC right and
are there any specific techniques for
handling high volume of data if we want
to handle high volume of data then I
would like to say that okay we
definitely want to paralyze the data
consumption so I mean in rting way what
do we do is that okay we can actually
create multiple data injection sources
and these sources will listen to the
Upstream services and then consume data
in in parallel because right if you just
use one through two personage I mean I
mean the data from all these data
sources then it it won't work right
because there may may be a lot of data
right so to allow ring wave to consume
data large volume data from off stream
Services then definitely we really want
to paralyze the system and we actually
support distribution or distributing
distributing the data inest in different
machines and definitely also works I've
heard the term data connectors what are
they and what is the role they play in
data quality and
consistency okay so actually different
systems may use different connectors
right I mean if you talk about to data
warehouses like Snowflake and rare shift
they actually have their own connector I
don't know the fundamental technology of
their systemss how they build the data
connector I don't know I don't know that
part but they actually have their own
connector like let's say in snowflakes
they actually have a project called
snowpipe which allows people to do
streaming ingestion directly from
different systems into snowflake but in
streaming bases like riding wave like
probably casb I'm not sure about that
but yeah let's say inside of a streaming
dat basist then typically we can consume
data from messaging cues directly let's
say Kafka like say kesis right because
in Kafka they actually have Kafka
connector right we do not need to manage
the the connectors on our own right but
if you want to consume data from let's
say database systems like myql and
postgress streaming deves typically use
divisum a CDC tool that allows people to
directly capture the data changes from
the Upstream database
Services okay and is realtime data
enrichment handle how do you manage to
do that oh data enrichment well there
are actually two types of data
enrichment one thing here that is kind
of simple that is probably do some basic
transformation right data transformation
like filtering like aggregation and like
probably projection right so that's kind
of basic data enrichment I think well
for all kinds of streaming databases
like okay casb resing wave pipeline DV
it can be done easily because well this
kind of like jobs well or probably
queres are kind of simple and we do not
need to match large states but another
very interesting type of data instrument
is called joins right let's say that
true if I if I have multiple data
sources Kafka myo and the postgress I
really want to join the data from all
these data services right then how I can
do that I definitely want to do drawings
right if I want to joins then in stream
basis in stream processing we actually
need to match large state right large
inter internal State and if we want to
match large internal State then we
actually need to have let's say
mechanics like checkpoint and the Fatal
recovery right and different streaming
databases the is for checkpoint and fail
recovery differently for them in ring
wave I mean we St data in S3 so that we
actually rely on S3 to do all kinds of
the fail recovery and but in some other
databases like streaming databases like
casb they actually have their local
store they actually store their data in
the local machine so they actually need
to frequently do checkpointing and
purist the data from the local state to
the remote storage like S3 and every
time a system crash that they actually
need to think about okay how I can pull
data from the remote storage like S3 to
my local state and that's how this
streaming dat Bas is do with the
checkpoint and F recovery but back to
the data enrichment yes the difficult
part of data enrichment that's for how
the streaming databas can do joins and
the joins is definitely a key challenge
in all streames and if we want to joins
efficiently then we need to think a lot
about the fail recovery and checko and
definitely people also need to think
about the optimizers because the joint
ordering can also affect the performance
anyways well data Improvement is
definitely a pretty challenging task if
specifically refer to joins I'd like to
double click a bit on that particular
topic about joints can you explain why
joints are difficult in a streaming
database maybe if you take a concrete
example where you got a data source
which is coming from Kafka and another
from maybe a postris database yeah we
can actually use let's say the ad
monetization example let's say that okay
we have click stream right and the other
one is a impression stream now we have
two stream one is Click stream and the
other one is impression stream and as a
platform I really want to join these two
data streams together because I want to
see okay which impression leads to which
click right so that I can monetize the
ad right so if I want to do such kind of
drawing right then what I want to do is
that okay I need to maintain two hash
tables actually I want to build a hash
table for the impression stream and a
hash table for the click stream and and
every time a new t comes in into let's
say the impression stream then I need to
check okay whether there's a match in
the hasal for the click stream if
there's a match I know that okay there's
one impression that to lead to one click
right and similarly if the new Tu comes
in from the click stream I need to check
okay whether it's a match in the
impression stream if there's MCH then it
means that okay there's an impression
that leads to this click right so I have
always need to maintain internal States
the internal these two hash tables in my
streaming database then problem here
that okay how I can maintain these two
hash tables right I probably can
maintain them in memory but the problem
here that okay let's say that my machine
crashes if my machine crashes then all
memory data will get lost that a big
problem right because which means that
if I want to reduce such kind of
compination then I need to rebu these
two hash tables right let's say that if
I have let's say a s days data right
right if I need to P seven days data it
means that they actually need to
recompute from Scrat from seven days ago
right from the data that was generally
seven days ago and it will take a long
time I don't know but probably 1 hour
probably two hour probably even one day
right because that may be huge amount of
data so the thing here that we need to
think about how we want to persist these
hash tabls or how we want to persist
these internal States and that's a key
challenge that the streaming database
need to handle and yeah back to what I
said earlier and there are different
ways people probably just use let's say
the local disk to persist the data and
parly do checkpoint into remote machines
but in some other systems they may
directly persist the data or purist the
state in remote disk remote SSD up not
sorry not remote SSD but remote object
stall and then they use a local machine
as a cache to serve as a cache to
accelerate curve processing right and I
guess if you stored only in the local
machine challenges around horizontal
scaling yeah so that's horizontal
scaling is also quite relevant to how we
want to do persistence because well I
mean if you want to store data in local
machines then let's say that if I want
to scale from one machine to three
machines now the problem become thaty
and now we want to do scating then the
problem become that key we actually need
to partition the local state into let's
say three pieces and then shift these
three pieces into the three machines
right three newly created machines and
then to do scaling right so that
definitely works but you actually need
to deal with let's say the data
consistency right and also you need to
think about okay there are probably some
down time during the data migration
State migration right but the other way
which is adopted by region wave that is
Will persist the directly process the
data in remote storage
if we do that then scaling becomes that
okay we can just create three new
machines and ask these three new
machines to directly reach uh to
directly Access Data from the remote
object stall there will be no data
migration there have be no State
migration this it from one machine to
three machines these three newly created
machines will directly access the remote
object install to F the states so yeah
these are two fundamentally different
way to do horizontal scaling yep makes
sense just wanted to touch on indexing
before we move into the next section is
indexing any different in streaming data
bases and how does that impact the
overall query performance or data
retrieval well indexing actually works
in a similar way as a trational database
system but I think the indexing
mechanism is also varies based on yeah
what kind of streaming database you are
referring to and even in in traditional
databases well different databases may
handle those index is differently right
in some databases their index is
actually a synchronous index which means
that where the index is actually not
consistent with the base table but in
some databases but they always guarantee
the consistent or the synchronous index
which means that the index always
reflects the latest data right so yeah
these are two different ways and in
streaming thees well definitely this is
also tradeoff in some streaming
databases for the index is a synchronous
but in databases like if it's
synchronous but the trail here that key
I mean if you want to maintain
synchronous inex definitely you probably
really want to have more comination
resources right you definitely need to
consume more comination resources yeah
that's a tradeoff when you say it's
synchronous indexes what you mean is
basically the index gets updated as the
data gets updated yeah that's right well
let's say that if I insert a new T into
a base table right or table in a
database right then I should see this
data in the index build on top of that
table right I want to see that tle but
the problem here that in some database
is well I mean they do not really have a
consistent synchronous index and then
the index may be kind of stale if you
insert a tuo into a database table the
tupo may not be directly reflected in
that index they maybe after 1 minute you
will see that table but there's no
guarantee at all qued we'll move on to
the next section which is around
security are there any fundamental
differences in how security concerns are
addressed in a streaming database
compared to Conventional databases or
conventional security models applied I
would say probably there's no much
difference because well yeah again where
security saying where it's s it VAR is
based on the companies and different
company may have different policies for
examp some companies want to make sure
that all data is encrypted and they
always use TRS to guarant guarantee the
security of the data transformation and
in streamings we Al yeah definitely we
all always need to obey those kind of
regulations or compliance you oby this
kind of compliance so I would say that's
where there's no big difference how do
you handle out of order events or data
coming in out of order in a streaming
database yeah that's a very interesting
question right well because in the in a
conventional dat base people do not
really do care about okay what is all of
all order right well yeah I just didn't
instore data and there's no order at all
right the conventional database is deal
with transactions but in streaming
databases we deal with orders which mean
that okay if two it may result in
different results right it may these two
different results so we use a technology
called Watermark to guarantee that with
the even if the data comes in different
orders we do see a consistent result
yeah let me give you a very concrete
example let's say that if I want to
account how many sensor events there
occurred within the last 10 seconds
right if I connect ring with with
different sensors right sensors may send
data in different orders right because
of the network issues because all all
kinds of issues right this data can be
disordered but reading with or probably
some other streaming databases right we
always want to display the correct
results to the users even if the data is
disordered right then all these
streaming databases actually use a
concept C the water mark to process the
disorder data basically what the
strategy is that okay we will actually
maintain a buffer to capture the data
within the that is ingested within a
within a certain Peri of time and if a
data comes late let's say that if I want
to count how many Tes occurred within
the last 10 second but a new tle just to
come in I probably insert this tle back
to the prace window window right then
what will happen is that okay I will
actually modify the result maintained by
the window right so that's how it works
we use a mechanism called Watermark yeah
so what you're saying is there's a
concept called as Watermark which
basically allows you to say that for a
certain period it will take in all the
events so even if an event comes in late
but as long as it's within that water
mark range it will be included in that
uh query result yes what happens to the
events which come after the watermark
period so that event well I think well
it's kind of depending on the impation
but in some cases well the lat event
will just be dis discarded yeah
basically will be ignored but in some
cases it was probably buffered yeah okay
so you've got a buffer time where you
wait for any events which are coming
late you still included if it's outside
of that buffer period you don't include
it that's right right how do you manage
data D duplication yeah in some Services
where there are duplicated data right so
let's say that if I maintain a cka right
well and there maybe there are some
duplicated cka for for various reason
right because probably I just rebuilded
CA right I probably every set of that
right so basically writing with and some
other streaming databases case good DB
and many others we actually were track
the offset of the data so basically we
will check okay which data I'm currently
processing am I processing the 100 data
right or 100 Tu right if I'm processing
that if I saw that the new Tu coming and
it is still 100 tle then I should
discard it it right that's how the
streaming database is De with the data
duplication all right so use something
called a offset which allows you to have
a view of what has already been
processed oh yeah yeah I think we soft
yeah that's right that's right okay so
as an industry if you moved from
traditional conventional databases onto
stream processing or real time analytics
and now we've got stream databases and I
think Rising wave is where we have got
stream databases evolve into using cloud
or cloud-based streaming databases what
do you see in the future how do you see
streaming databases evolve going forward
well if you talk about a streaming
database a feature of streaming database
definitely I would like to say that okay
first all it be more powerful right
because well as I just mentioned well
very early in this talk well there was a
lot of stream processing engines right
so for newly buil streaming databases no
matter whether it's Casp materialized
Rising wave I believe yeah there are
still a long way to go because well I
mean conventional streaming processing
engines have already been built for
probably say there for 10 years right or
probably 10 plus years and definitely we
need to catch up with some
functionalities like I don't know Java
API probably with some python API right
all these kind things but in terms of
the architecture I would like say that
it's pretty interesting to see that okay
there may be a big change in the object
store if you pay attention to reinvent
this year 2023 you will know that he
actually announced this new technology
called S3 Express right so basically
what it means that S3 can provide single
digit MC latency and that be definitely
a game changer for all the streaming
databases which means that all and not
just the streaming I have to say that
all these Data Systems because that
means that we can actually store data in
cheap devices object stores and actually
can allow us to handle low lency
processing right because PR mentioned
that if we store data in S3 then every
time we access to S3 then it will
probably incur pretty high latency 100
millisecond latency or probably 200
millisecond latency which is not
tolerable and then we actually need to
build a caching layer to guarantee that
okay most of the requests were hidden in
the query and can be responded in pretty
low latency but if S3 chance award and
provides a single digit millisecond
latency then we actually can safly store
data probably all my data in S3 right
and then I mean we can guarantee a user
that we can always guarantee the user
that they can see the freshest results
right and answer the CES in very very
low l you can see without incurring high
expense so definitely I would like to
say that with the hardware change the S3
Express may change the streaming
database and definitely probably the
entire database world and the SE CH I
would like to say is that many people
talk about unified B and stream
processing right which means that case
they probably don't really want to
purchase two different systems one for
handling streaming data and the other
one for handling batch data so they are
advocating for a un ified system that
can process both streaming datab
streaming data and bat data so I do
think that that's definitely a direction
that streaming database should go for
right because look not streaming
database is are used to process written
data right but more data is stored
inside of streaming data database then
we need to think about how we can serve
this data to the users right let's say
that if a user really want to check the
history results we actually don't really
want to let the users to push this data
into some snowflake or probably r shift
because that's not convenient right so
definitely we really want to have the
users to do all this batch processing
and stream processing in one single
system isn't spark streaming a unified
framework for batch and stream
processing so are you saying that you'll
see more streaming databases going in
that direction yeah something that well
I mean that's a good question in Spar we
actually have both batch and stream
processing because for for Spar
ultimately it's designed for B
processing and it also have a component
called Spar streaming which is actually
designed for stream processing right so
nowadays people can think okay can
consider a spar as let's say a unified
batch and stream processing engine right
but definitely I would like to remind
that kpar is the engine it's a stream
processing engine but the unified
streaming and a bat concept does not
just exist in the engine world or in the
Big Data World it also exist in the
database world let's take snowflake as
an example right well snowflake recently
announced the snowpipe and they also
have the say the life table right the
life table is essentially a concept of
the stream processing it B because what
it does incremental computation and it
will refresh the results for the users
right automatically for the users so I
believe that case the unified stream
processing and bat processing has also
happened in the streaming database and I
believe that some streaming databases
have already started implenting that
part right got it okay got it so so what
we're saying is basically we've got
unified batch and stream processing in
the Stream processing world but not in
the streaming databases world so we will
see that happening yeah we will see that
happening in the streaming database
World okay excellent we have covered a
lot of ground over here we have covered
the fundamentals of streaming databases
we have understood how it differs from
stream processing we have delved into
the architecture and design patterns
used in streaming databases and we have
also looked at some of the use cases for
streaming databases thanks a lot for
that Yen if people want to find out more
about what you're up to where can they
go well they can definitely Vis our
official website ringwave tocom
and definitely they can also go to
GitHub and check out our GitHub reposer
and definitely the easiest way is to
join our slack Community reading
wave.com
slack that's a website and you can join
our slack community and directly pay me
and then we can talk a lot about okay
stream processing stream Bas the future
of data engineering thing yeah y thank
you for coming on the show it's been a
real pleasure this is bries Aman for
software engineering radio thank you for
listening thanks for listening to SC
radio an educational program brought to
you by It software magazine for more
about the podcast including other
episodes visit our website at se-
radio.net to provide feedback you can
comment on each episode on the website
or reach us on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter
or through our slack Channel at
seo. slack.com you can also email us at
team
c-rnli other episodes of SC radio is
licensed under Creative Commons license
2.5 thanks for
[Music]